This is the Falcon 9 launching from Vandenberg Air Force Base in California.
这是猎鹰九号从加州范登堡空军基地升空的画面
This particular launch produced a spectacular display above the Californian night sky.
这次发射在加州的夜空留下了一道壮观景象
Rocket launches have always been a fascinating spectacle.
火箭发射本身就是很壮观的
But every now and then, they produce stunning displays like this.
但我们平常所见的大都是这种普通的发射画面
But what is causing such an unusual effect?
那这种特殊的景象又是怎样形成的呢？
In this video we are going to look at a phenomenon known as the Twilight Effect.
本期视频我们将了解什么是“暮光效应”
We are also going to look at what causes this effect and why we don’t see it happen very often.
我们将了解这种现象是如何产生的，以及它为何不常见
In order for the Twilight Effect to occur,
想要看到暮光效应
the rocket in question needs to launch around 30 minutes before sunrise or after sunset.
火箭发射的时间必须在日出前30分钟或日落后30分钟内
As the rocket rises out of the night sky, it starts to escape the Earth’s shadow.
火箭在夜空中上升时，会渐渐离开地球的阴影区
The rocket’s exhaust plume is then illuminated by the high altitude sunlight
而火箭的尾气也会被高空的阳光照亮
which hasn’t yet been blocked by the Earth.
而那些尾气仍处在地球阴影之外
To an observer on the ground, the area around them is in darkness,
对于地面上的观察者来说，天虽然已经黑了
but the rocket’s exhaust plume is illuminated, making it stand out against the dark night sky.
但火箭的尾气被照亮，在漆黑的夜空中就格外显眼
As the rocket gets higher and higher, the atmospheric pressure drops,
而随着火箭越飞越高，大气压力逐渐降低
causing the exhaust plume to expand out into a much wider trail.
尾气的扩散也越来越宽
The upper level winds whip the exhaust trail around into a corkscrew shape
高空风将尾气吹成螺旋形状
and the small particles in the exhaust plume diffract the sunlight to produce orange and blue colors,
高空的微小粒子又把阳光色散成橙色或者蓝色
making the effect even more spectacular.
让暮光效应的现象更加绚丽多彩
Rocket launches that produce the Twilight Effect are very rare.
火箭发射时产生的暮光效应非常少见
Since 1958, over 1,800 missiles and rocket boosters have been launched from Vandenberg,
1958年以来，超过1800发导弹和火箭从范登堡基地发射
but only a few of those launches have produced the Twilight Effect.
但其中只有很少部分产生了暮光效应
One of the most spectacular examples of the effect was seen during a recent launch of the Falcon 9.
其中最好的例子就是最近猎鹰九号的发射
During this launch, the Twilight Effect allowed us to see the first stage
该次发射中，暮光效应让我们清楚地看到了火箭一级
and the two fairings seperating from the second stage.
还看到了火箭整流罩从二级上分离的画面
The puffs of smoke coming from the first stage
而一级火箭上噗噗噗的气流
are cold gas thrusters which are used to steer the rocket in the right direction.
则是火箭上的氮气调姿发动机在调整火箭的姿态
A previous SpaceX launch in 2017 created a similar display in the night sky
在2017年太空叉还有一次发射也产生了暮光效应
which caused many observers in California to report UFO sightings and missile attacks.
加州很多人看到后报警说看到了UFO或导弹袭击
OBSERVER: Bro, the world's about to end, bro
吃瓜群众甲：老铁，世界末日来了，咋办老铁
OBSERVER: Aliens!
吃瓜群众乙：外星人入侵啦！
OBSERVER: What the "FALCON" is this?
吃瓜群众丙：What the "FALCON" is this?
So although twilight launches are a rare occurrence, they allow us to appreciate the beauty of our Earth
因此，尽管暮光效应不多见，但它能让我们感受到地球之美
and remind us of how amazing spaceflight really is.
也能让我们知道火箭发射是件多么有趣的事情
If you have any more questions on how the Twilight Effect occurs let me know in the comments below.
如果你还有什么问题，欢迎在评论区讨论
If you enjoyed this video and would like to contribute to Primal Space, please visit Patreon.com/PrimalSpace
如果喜欢这个视频，想资瓷原作，欢迎去下面链接资瓷一下
where we will be doing a giveaway of a Saturn V LEGO set once we reach 50 Patrons.
满50个赞助就抽乐高版土星五号哦
So make sure you’re subscribed so you can join the discussion as we continue to learn more about all things space.
字幕翻译给虫，记得点赞投币收藏转发分享关注充电哦
Thank you very much for watching and I’ll see you in the next video.
感谢观看，下期视频见